- [Voiceover] Euler continued to investigate
او voiceover ] [ اولر استمر في التحقيق
properties of numbers, specifically
خصائص الارقام , بالتحديد
the distribution of prime numbers.
توزيع الارقام الاولية .
One important function he defined
واحد اهم وظيفته تعريف
is called the phi function.
فاي فاي وظيفة تسمى .
It measures the breakability of a number.
انها تقيس breakability من عدد .
So, given a number, say N,
لذا , بالنظر الى عدد , تقول , &quot;
it outputs how many integers are less than or equal to N
والنتائج كم integers هي اقل من او مساويا ل&quot;
that do not share any common factor with N.
اي انه لا نشارك العامل المشترك مع ن .
For example, if we want to find the phi of eight
على سبيل المثال , اذا اردنا ان نجد فاي فاي من 8
we look at all values from one to eight,
نظرنا الى كل من واحد الى ثمانية , القيم
then we count how many integers
ثم احصينا عدد integers
eight does not share a factor greater than one with.
لا نشارك بثمانية اكبر بعامل واحد .
Notice six is not counted,
لاحظوا , ليس بعد ستة
because it shares a factor of two,
لانها اثنين , يشاركنا
while one, three, five and seven are all counted,
بينما , ثلاثة , خمسة وكل احصاء , سبعة
because they only share a factor of one.
لانهم يتشاركون عاملا واحد فقط .
Therefore, phi of eight equals four.
لذلك , فاي فاي من ثمانية يساوي اربعة .
What's interesting is that calculating
المثير للاهتمام هو ان تحسب
the phi function is hard, except in one case.
هذه هي وظيفة فاي فاي من الصعب , الا في حالة واحدة .
Look at this graph.
انظروا الى هذا الرسم البياني .
It is a plot of values of five,
انه لمن خمسة قيم ,
over integers from one to 1,000.
اكثر من واحد الى 1000 integers .
Now, notice any predictable pattern?
الان , لاحظ اي نمط يمكن التنبؤ بها ?
The straight line of points along the top
الخط المستقيم على اعلى من نقاط
represent all the prime numbers.
تمثل جميع الارقام الاولية .
Since prime numbers have no factors greater than one,
ليس لدي منذ الارقام الاولية احد العوامل , اكبر
the phi of any prime number, P,
واي فاي فاي , بي , ممتاز
is simply P minus one.
هو ببساطة بي ناقص واحد .
To calculate phi of seven, a prime number,
فاي فاي ان تحسب عدد من سبعة , و,
we count all integers, except seven,
نحن نحسب كل integers , باستثناء سبعة ,
since none of them share a factor with seven.
منذ ان ايا منهم مشاركة عامل بسبعة .
Phi of seven equals six.
فاي فاي من 7 = ستة .
So, if you're asked to find phi of 21,377, a prime number,
لذا , اذا كنت من ايجاد فاي فاي , وعدد من 21,377 ,
you would only need to subtract one
سنحتاج للتخلص من فقط
to get the solution, 21,376.
ان الحل , 21,376 .
Phi of any prime is easy to compute.
ممتاز لاي فاي فاي سهلة للحساب .
This leads to an interesting result based on the fact
هذا يقود الى مثيرة للاهتمام ذلك يعتمد على حقيقة
that the phi function is also multiplicative.
ان فاي فاي وظيفة هو ايضا multiplicative .
That is, phi A times B equals phi A times phi B.
لذلك , فاي فاي اوقات B فاي فاي فاي فاي بي تساوى لمرات .
If we know some number N is the product of two primes,
اذا نحن نعرف بعض هو رقم &quot; المنتج primes , من اثنين
P one and P two, then phi of N
بي بي , ومن ثم فاي فاي &quot;
is just the value of phi for each prime multiplied together,
فقط لقيمة فاي فاي كل تضاعفت الاولية معا,
or P one minus one, times P two minus one.
او بي بي احد ناقص ناقص واحد , اثنين مرة واحدة .